Stefan Wawrowski papers CPAA.90.17
Connecticut Polish American Archives
Stefan Wawrowski papers
1945-1984
CPAA.90.17
Connecticut Polish American Archives
1.5 Linear feet
The collection consists of personal papers of Stefan Wawrowski, a prisoner of Dachau concentration camp, who immigrated to the United States in 1950. Mr. Wawrowski settled in Hartford, Connecticut and was active in many Polish American political and cultural organizations. The collection is enriched by many photographs from the Dachau concentration camp after libration in 1945 and from Displaced Person camp where Mr. Wawrowski stayed and worked in the camp administration until he received a refugee status and was allowed to immigrate to the United States. Also family photographs from Poland and photos from various local events are included.
Wawrowski, Stefan
Scope and Contents note
The collection consists of Mr. Wawrowski's personal papers, memoirs and documents related to imprisonment in the Dachau concentration camp. Also included are documents from his stay and work in administration of the Displaced Person's camp and his immigration to the US and further activities in Polish American organizations in Hartford and New Britain area in Connecticut. Collection contains of photographs from Dachau after liberation and from his family that was left in Poland - wife and son.
Biographical/Historical note
Mr. Stefan Wawrowski was born in Plock in Poland on June 23, 1903. He was a freedom fighter and already in 1917 he joined the Polish Military Organization. He married Leona Stanislawa Zielinska in 1926 and had one son Tadeusz born in 1935. Mr. Wawrowski worked as a telephone technician before the WW II. In 1939 he joined the Polish Underground Army; he was captured by Germans in 1940 and sent to Dachau concentration camp, prisoner number 4684, and was liberated in 1945 by the Allied forces. Mr. Wawrowski stayed at the Polish Displaced Person's camp, where he worked till he immigrated to the US in 1950 and lived in Hartford, Connecticut. Mr. Wawrowski was employed by the Royal Business Machines Company till his early retirement in 1962, due to disability. He was active in many Polish organizations the Polish World War II Veterans Post no. 10 in Hartford, member of the Polish American Congress district of Connecticut, and a president of the Polish National Fund Committee of Connecticut. For his active participation in a various organizations he received several distinguished awards: the Silver and the Gold Cross of Merit, the Knight Cross of the Most Distinguished Order of Polonia Restituta. Mr. Wawrowski never reunited with his family in Poland. He died on August 17, 1984 and is buried in Bloomfield, CT.
Conditions Governing Access note
The collection is open for research.
Arrangement note
The original arrangement of the material was kept.
Custodial History note
After passing of Mr. Stefan Wawrowski the material was forwarded to the Connecticut Polish American Archives by Mr. Thaddeus Maliszewski.
Correspondence.; Dachau (Concentration camp); Memoirs.; Polish Americans -- Connecticut; World War, 1939-1945 -- Concentration camps -- Germany; World War, 1939-1945 -- Personal narratives, Polish; World War, 1939-1945 -- Prisoners and prisons, German; World War, 1939-1945 -- Refugees
- Wawrowski, Stefan - Certificate of death and prayer cards., August 17, 1984 (Box 1, Folder 1)
- Wawrowski, Stefan – Obituary and In Memory funeral book., August 22, 1984 (Box 1, Folder 2)
- Wawrowski, Stefan – personal belongings i.e. watch, wedding ring, army uniform emblem, notebook, surname etymology. It also includes board with mounted rosary, cross, prisoner's number from Dachau camp,and Polish eagle., undated (Box 1, Folder 3)
- Wawrowski, Stefan – personal correspondence with family in Poland and friends., 1981-1984 (Box 1, Folder 4)
- Wawrowski, Stefan – clippings about him., 1980 (Box 1, Folder 5)
- Wawrowski, Stefan – documents related to imprisonment in Dachau, concentration camp; his stay at POW’s camp near Munich; immigration to the US. Documents are in German, English and Polish., 1943-1964 (Box 1, Folder 6)
- Wawrowski, Stefan – various ID and membership cards, certificates., 1949-1970 (Box 1, Folder 7)
- Wawrowski, Stefan – documentation from International Refugee Organization, birth certificate, marriage certificate, baptismal records., 1948-1950 (Box 1, Folder 8)
- Wawrowski, Stefan – documents from Dachau concentration camp imprisonment and discharge., 1945-1949 (Box 1, Folder 9)
- Wawrowski, Stefan – correspondence with United Nations and German authorities related to receiving funds for WWII concentration camps disabilities., 1969-1973 (Box 1, Folder 10)
- Play in one act. Based on a true story from Gestapo building in Plock during German occupation. [written by Stefan Wawrowski?], 1940 (Box 1, Folder 11)
- Wawrowski, Stefan – writings about camp life includes notes on Bishop Michal Kozal, who died in Dachau by lethal injection, was beatified by the Pope John Paul II., between 1945 - 1947 (Box 1, Folder 12)
- Ostatnie dni Dachau [Last days of Dachau] – wspomnienia Stefana Wawrowskiego i innych wiezniow., 1945 (Box 1, Folder 13)
- Wawrowski, Stefan – Memoirs and description from every day at Dachau, includes drawing of prisoners’ uniforms and emblems and photographs., 1946-1947 (Box 1, Folder 14)
- Wawrowski, Stefan – description of camp’s hospital (in Polish)., 1947 (Box 1, Folder 15)
- Wawrowski, Stefan – description of work units, last days of camp, and typical day at the camp, list of some prisoners., 1946 (Box 1, Folder 16)
- Set of four drawings/caricatures by Stanislaw Toegel, illustrating Polish Army soldiers during WWII., 1945 (Box 1, Folder 17)
- Collection of photographs of Stefan Wawrowski his wife Stanislawa and their son Tadeusz., 1938-1980 (Box 2)
- Collection of photographs from Dachau camp and Polish POW’s after WWII., 1945-1947 (Box 2)
- Cross and a holy picture., undated (Box 2)
- Clippings, pictures, and pamphlets related to history of Poland., 1960-1980 (Box 2)
- Collection of photographs from social gatherings, veterans anniversaries, and Polonia events., 1960-1980 (Box 3)
- General Casimir Pulaski Memorial Monument – anniversary booklet, Hartford., 1976 (Box 3)
- Poland’s Millennium of Christianity - pamphlets., 1966 (Box 3)